the vietnam war and the push for u.s involvement
was a result of the gulf of tompkin incident
a lie the iraq war famously is a result of lies
wars in somalia are a result of lies
the second world war and the german invasion of
poland was a result of carefully constructed lies
that is war by media let us ask ourselves of
the complicit media which is the majority of
the mainstream press what is the average
death count attributed to each journalist
that was uh julian assange at the very top at an
anti-war speech in 2010 in london and of course
um anton karis from the third man the theme
song i'm randy critical to surrender critical
live on the fly with a special assange countdown
to freedom uh which will be played on various uh
channels and you know websites and radio stations
so we're not going to identify them right here
except for to say uh we have a very special show
today as we go into the holidays this is actually
uh being recorded on the anniversary of the
assassination of john f kennedy which i just
now realized uh but we have uh and we're going
to have ladies first we have uh we're introducing
wise uh colleen rally who's been on this show
several times she is a whistleblower former fbi
special agent and a council and she's a recipient
of the prestigious sam adams award uh john keriaku
whose books he's written about 10 books
also a whistleblower a recipient i think
craig murray gave him the award in 2016. uh the
sam adams award and uh john is uh going off to
germany uh to present a book about whistleblowers
and um certainly last but not least uh someone
that we all admire and respect and and and you
know he he daniel ellsberg has been so gracious
and so generous with his time uh but
there was a five year lapse where i was
afraid to ask him because i know how busy he is uh
to do this show i've done about 200 assange shows
uh but uh he's joining us again from uh berkeley
california and john let's start off because we're
kind of free forming this how important is daniel
ellsberg in this movement to uh free assange
i i don't want to embarrass dan of course uh
but i'll repeat what i've said publicly um
dan is the godfather of modern day
national security whistleblowing
if dan hadn't done what he did with the pentagon
papers none of us would have been able to do what
we did later and the parallels between what dan
did so long ago now 50 years ago and what julian
did are striking listen julian's a smart guy
uh julian knows history he's studied history
he knew about dan and dan's uh heroic actions uh
by releasing the pentagon papers i i know that
dan was uh was a source of inspiration for julian
just like he was a source of inspiration for all
the rest of us i i'm i i'm honored to know him you
know i still i still name drop dad with my friends
hit like i know dan ellsberg and i consider him
to be a friend you know i can't i still can't
believe that i'm friends with dan ellsberg
it means so much to me and uh and people
people understand that they realize that because
now they have a real appreciation for what he did
dan knew what the consequences were and he did
it anyway because it was the right thing to do
and that has inspired so many more people to do
the right thing the least of which is certainly
not uh julian assange uh colleen as well uh
you've known dance as you guys are friends um
has you been an inspiration to a lot of people
including yourself well yes of course um the one
thing that i i find very unusual unsadly unusual
about daniel ellsberg is he's a survivor you know
whistleblowing is such a a traumatic and risky and
uh in some way soul you know wrenching situation
especially if you lose even your your own family
and friends etc that you know he's one of the very
few um who not only survived that experience and
and actually was able to turn it into something
good and use it but also he's the duracell battery
yeah and he's he's never looked back and it's just
been straight forward i think julian assange you
know it's it's so difficult for him now in prison
this way um but i think he has similar strength of
character as daniel ellsberg and um and and maybe
you know we could even say people like mandela you
know who actually did go through that kind of a
prison experience and were able to come out of it
and and uh so i mean we have to cross our fingers
right now but obviously this is what we're aiming
for we're aiming for surviving truth-telling
and then continuing on and it's never been
so difficult as it is in the present time
well dan let me ask you this uh you've inspired so
many whistleblowers uh ed snowden john uh colleen
julian who inspired you when you went forward
i know uh there was an anti-war activist
who has the same name randy keller i believe
that that inspired you to go forward but what
prior to that was it that subconsciously drove you
to actually do it listen let me uh back off there
for one moment because i didn't expect and that's
not clear to me why we're starting this off with
such a gratifying praise for my friends here but
the funny thing is as i'm looking at this screen
i'm looking at two people that i was talking about
this morning i had a two hour zoom meeting with a
class at umass amherst uh by run by professor
chris appy in the course of that i had time
enough to talk about heroes of mine here but i
uh in two two contexts one that the example that
the question arises as to when you should not
only be a whistleblower but when you it is is
simply wrong to uh prosecute a whistleblower
the most obvious case would be when you're
revealing criminality and the idea that you can
be prosecuted for colleen is the lawyer here but
the idea that you can be prosecuted for revealing
crime by the government is something deeply wrong
with that system well i was saying nothing in
the world pretty much is as illegal as criminal
as torture as i understand it uh it's known
as juice or use colgans which is uh closely
non-derogatory uh non-derivable uh criminality in
the sense that no parliament no executive branch
no court can make it legal uh it's uh like piracy
or a few other things that are odd historic things
that come in there but torture cannot be made
legal and then you can argue about what is torture
but then there's lots of things that are really
beyond argument and that's what the us was doing
uh in this case i said how many people hundreds at
least a thousand more john would know better were
aware that what we were doing was criminal not
only in international law but in our constitution
and in domestic law that there was no way to make
it legal and of all the hundreds of people who
knew that we were doing that one to my knowledge
went to prison and that was the one who revealed
inadvertently or otherwise revealed the name of
a torturer a covert actor uh as i understand it
he was not aware that the person's status at that
time was still protected but anyway he was charged
with with doing that and went to prison having
in fact revealed somebody in the torture program
and having earlier described the waterboarding
as torture uh for which i think the cia will
never forgive him as he probably says just as they
will never forgive snowden they will never forgive
chelsea manning for revealing that we
were turning people over to torture
under obama knowing there was for torture which
is as illegal as doing the torture ourselves and
uh so she spent seven and a half years in prison
so anyway i was describing john in those terms as
uh having been dealt with very very badly by his
country and by his former agency but in general
constitutionally by the president by everybody and
uh in a way that should not happen in this country
but i was also mentioning colleen as he's uh who
is that i said the word fissile whistleblower
was pretty much legitimized for the first
time by a time cover with persons of the year
that was not me whistleblowers colleen rowley's
face on that cover and right here just yeah oh
really okay well just between us uh not to
not to derogatory anyway the two other women
who were there very technically as i read their
account for enron i think another one i'm not
sure i would call them whistleblowers they were
truth tellers but correct me if i'm wrong colleen
my understanding is that they told the truth
to their bosses and not to outside the agency
uh the corporation which uh about which
was giving incriminating information
again tell me if i'm wrong but i think the other
two who acted admirably within their organization
did not take the step of risking their careers
being ostracized being possibly even prosecuted
by going outside that organization to hold
it accountably and colleen did do that and uh
and as i understand it not not to go into it
too much i think she experienced the kind of not
entirely but ostracism within her own organization
the fbi that every truth-teller who is revealing
uh wrongdoing by her or his own group is risking
ostracism and most people will not take that risk
so uh again as i say i'm looking at two people
who very much do exemplify i would say the best
in america the possibility of american
citizenship which is too little observed
john do you want to say something thank you
for that dan um that that means a lot to me
you know one of the things that dan uh taught me
uh early on was that uh there's a greater good uh
there's a greater good with whistleblowing
uh one of the things that i learned
from a recent study on whistleblowers is that
there that whistleblowers have a much more
highly defined sense of right and wrong than
the general population this is something borne
out in psychological uh studies and so when
a whistleblower is considering blowing the
whistle on waste fraud abuse or illegality or
threats to the public health or public safety
um he or she takes into consideration
that that greater good and um
you know eventually history is going to catch
up with the issue and with everybody else uh
you may be vilified the way dan was vilified the
way julian assange is being vilified right now
but eventually the rest of the world will catch up
we've seen this happen throughout history
and uh i think that's one of the reasons why
julian has been so steadfast in in
his belief that he did the right thing
god knows the cost has been high we see what
the poor man is is undergoing uh nils melser
has said repeatedly nils mills are the the un
special rapporteur on torture has said repeatedly
that what julian has been uh experiencing is a
form of torture we all know that that the way
the united states practices solitary confinement
is a form of torture we know that these cmus these
communications management units that we have in
our in our medium and maximum security prisons
is a form of of torture but uh the government
doesn't yet have an appreciation for the fact
that that none of that matters julian is tougher
than everybody gives him credit for being
just like dan was tougher than everybody gave
him credit for being you know dan stood up to
a president arguably one of the the most powerful
and corrupt presidents in modern american history
julian has stood up to what three different
presidents so far so there's this odd way
that people have a tendency to underestimate
our resolve and they do that i think randy
at their own peril colleen uh jump in
there i'll fly on the wall on this one
well you know i think in any whistleblowers
uh trajectory if you want to call it that from
start to finish a lot a lot of times it
begins with a certain amount of naivety
where people are honestly believe so much in
that there is right and wrong and that they
it's really hard to believe that you can be
in these situations like orwell you know i
think orwell has a quote where you become a
traitor telling the truth in an empire of lies
and i mean that's really really i think um a
telling thing right now in the empire of lies
and you're a traitor to tell the truth but
you know it's hard to think that at the start
you don't think that um just outing torture for
heaven's sakes you know everybody would think okay
if you're torturing that's right you know very
wrong and you can't believe that you can be the
one that's later smeared for the being the one who
told the truth about torture or other war crimes
it's hard to believe that you know i know we're
going to talk a little bit about the assange case
and a little bit about the fbi's informant yes
we're gonna do that in the second half here
i'm just gonna jump a little bit ahead because one
of the things that you know as the trajectory goes
on long before 9 11 and all of this started a
long before that towards the really you know
after a lot of years in the fbi i started to see
oh my gosh look what the what they're doing with
these informants they're operating murderers
in some cases you know and again you don't
think that you think okay everybody's going to
want to stop this as soon as we know that the
fbi's operating murderers that will end because
nobody will be for that and that's where again
this kind of at this trajectory the scales come
off your eyes and that's a real sad experience
to find out that people are so easily misled on
knowing right from wrong going back to what you
said it's really a depressing thing to see how
many other people can't stick to principles and
can't stick to you know what's right and what's
wrong in really horrible situations like an empire
of lies which is where which is orwell's term
but i think it's very fitting yes we're talking
with colleen riley uh john kayaku and mr daniel
ellsberg dan always say call you call your dan dan
um i'm going to ask everybody a stupid question
i'll start with you dan does anybody have any
regrets for coming forward dan i haven't met a
whistleblower and i've sought out many of them
uh including both of you i've sought them out
because they identify with them so much and i
know what they've gone through i've been through
that same trajectory which remember always is for
us a trajectory because we got access to that
information by having been loyal experience of
the cause of the organization up till then
or we wouldn't have gotten that access and
so then as colleen says the scales fall from your
eyes at some point they fall from a lot more eyes
than people those of people who who know what's uh
who actually speak out because it's one thing not
to know it as i've learned and we've all seen
in the last year especially anyone can believe
anything and anyone can deny anything practically
i mean look at what we're seeing in the country
it's rather uh staggering to some extent but we
all of us started we all started out believing
and a number of other people with us i'm sure uh
at least in the cases i know snowden for example
know that other colleagues knew just as much just
as well as because snowden's colleagues said this
is wrong you know we're listening to everyone
everything and this is wrong but what would
they do about it and as is always the case i have
children in college i have a mortgage on my house
right we're all settled here in this community
i just can't afford to break with all of that
and that's understandable to a larger extent
and the price generally is high i am one of the
few as i think referred to lucky one but i am
one of the few who in effect got away with it by
virtually a miracle of uh you know convergence
of circumstances that led to revelation of
criminality by the president which actually
led to dismissal of my case but very unusual
nixon wanted to put me in prison for 115 years
but didn't get it assange is facing 175 years
which would come to much the same thing if they
got us in but he is in prison now being held at
this point snowden permanent exile john was
a 30 month something like that in prison time
and chelsea manning seven and a half
years uh daniel hale right now uh
45 months ritter is at it i was referring
to him this morning to these students
the students today don't know his predecessor
it's crazy enough i i'm you know his predecessor
is nathan hale and it turned out i
asked for how many people in that class
knew the name i grew up with it of course and they
don't uh but i think of myself and i have said
this was his nathan hill uh daniel hill's
actual ancestor and uh he was the first person
prosecuted for giving information to americans
true information on the second it turns out i am
proud of that uh that heritage here he was hanged
by the british for being a spy for washington
and for a country that didn't actually yet
exist you know in a recognized form what
he was famous for as well as you and we know
saying as he was about to be hanged i regret
that i have but one life to give for my country
and what country was that that colin was saying
it was a country founded by traders like
nathan hale and washington and every signer
of the declaration of independence who are
all liable like nathan failed to be hanged
as traitors and several of them were traitors
to george iii who of whom may have been loyal
subjects just two years earlier or three years
earlier and they found a new loyalty to a country
that let's put it this way that doesn't have an
official secrets act officially that doesn't make
a traitor of someone who criticizes the leader
the monarch the government that's that's our
country supposedly so um uh it would be good if
they know this this history more i you asked me
randy who inspired me and i was thinking as
i heard these wonderful tributes when when
john was was saying we are inspired by i
was looking i said i've never heard from
colleen that she had me in mind and
i i don't know it yet exactly either
i was told by a biographer of julian that
he had been inspired by me and i said
how could that be i happen to know when
he was born it was a week when he was born
a week after my wife and i had spent 13 days
eluding the fbi uh successfully by the way uh
i don't know how how how you feel about that
kali about your organization but at one point
having eluded them for 13 days i asked my lawyer
lyndon boudin what is the fbi actually good at
and he said taking surrenders uh which which
i did after 13 days but the point was that um
julian had been born just after that so how
could i have inspired him and the biographer said
his mother was an anti-vietnam war activist in
australia and she in australia had uh had told him
stories of the anti-war movement in this country
including my name so that was very gratifying
to hear that it had been like that in my case um
there was in addition to randy keeler who was uh
as i've often told the story uh announced that he
was going to prison and that struck me very very
hard because i hadn't known he was on his way
to prison but uh and and confronted me with the
question all right what can i do to help in this
war now that i'm ready to go to prison like him
but just two days earlier another young man named
bob eaton was being sentenced for draft resistance
on craft resistance and i had stood in a vigil
line uh at this conference uh and and i think john
and and colleen will appreciate at that conference
of the war resistors thing i was reluctant to go
to that vigil because i was still working at rand
and i thought if my picture is is in front of the
philadelphia courthouse here uh standing in a
line it not only people will think i've gone mad
they will what a man who had access to these
higher-ups you know and could give them advice
is what could be less dignified than standing
on a hot afternoon in front of the courthouse
handing out leaflets but the change that made
in my life was well i was about to say i didn't
really want to go to that but i thought of saying
that i was sick something and then i thought well
the conference is still going on they'll
see that i'm not sick so i had to go and uh
then i found in the course of it that i wasn't
made of sugar after all i wasn't dissolving at
this indignity and i started handing out leaflets
to people in the courts and that actually changed
my life that was before randy getaway because it
was like when you said when you step over a line
in the recruiting office and that the marines
that i had done uh you step over the line and
for the rest of your career you're told you
stepped over that line you know don't complain
whatever happens you volunteer well in standing in
a vigil for bob eaton i was stepping over a line i
was joining a movement actively and that was a
critical moment before that i had been reading for
the last year or two because of a young woman that
i met who was a ghandian and it introduced me to
uh workshop gandhi barbara deming uh revolution
and equilibrium joan bondurant conquest
of violence and analysis of ghandian and in
particular of martin luther king's stride toward
freedom in particular where he tells about how
he with some misgivings joined the boycott uh in
connection with the buses in connection with rosa
parks and why was he reluctant because boycott
was something used by the white citizens councils
and uh against to boycott anybody who integrated
who allowed blacks to be in the restaurant he said
can i use the same tactic here you know the thing
and then he thought he remembered what gandhi had
said in others that to be silent in the face of
evil was to participate in it and that he had
to put his body on the line there and tell the
truth even when it did lead to great ostracism
and by the way when he came out against the war
in 1967 a year before he was killed or
due to the day before he was killed sorry
let me turn that out it's my wife um he he was
ostracized almost every paper in the country
denounced him for having hurt his standing with
the civil rights movement by taking on this
controversial controversial subject but as he said
i feel an obligation to do it he said there comes
a time when silence is culpability complicity and
thank you dan we have to take a quick break here
uh and for those listening in new york city uh
you can hear all of this on assange countdown
to freedom or next monday on a different network
we'll be right back after a quick musical break
do
okay i'm randy critical random critical
live on the fly here uh here on the um
progressive radio network and uh
on assange countdown to freedom
speaking to three special very special individuals
john kiriakou uh former cia intern whistleblower
uh colleen rally former fbi special agent turned
whistleblower truth teller and of course the um
what can you say daniel ellsberg the great uh
daniel ellsberg we are talking uh we're going
to continue talking about now the assange case
and by the way i want to ask you um this colleen
when dan was around and maybe he'll get to this
as well there was a lot more support for daniel
ellsberg when he came out and by the way jillian's
birthday is july 3rd 1971. his mother is colleen
uh colleen uh no it's a christine assange she's
been on the show three or four times as well
and she was an anti-war demonstrator but let me
ask you colleen why is it that julian doesn't
have the massive support that daniel ellsberg
had back in 1970 in this country um i've
actually written an article about this and even
though that was written uh five or six years ago
it's entitled recipe concocted for perpetual war
and i could not get it published in a mainstream
paper i sent it to 15 different papers and
eventually i it i put it on or it got put on
consortium news and the difference between i tried
to explain the difference between the vietnam war
and the current post-9 11 wars perpetual wars
and how they the the uh the ruling elite came
up with a recipe that makes it nearly impossible
for anyone to oppose it in the united states
obviously people around the world oppose u.s wars
but here in the united states we have very little
of the peace movement that grew during vietnam
so in vietnam it was just the opposite there
was very low opposition initially but then the
opposition grew and then it really grew after
the pentagon papers look at what's happened
here after the post-9 11 wars even with the
afghan papers being published which were very
very telling and before that with the wikileaks
uh documents being published uh essentially
support for war maybe little differences in what
places to to to drop the bombs on now we want to
go to war with russia and china and you know we're
we're tired of afghanistan and iraq the middle
east but now we've switched even bigger prize but
do you you never see on the mainstream news you
don't see anything like the cronkite moment where
somebody says even after the really bad uh ending
of the afghanistan war there should have been a
cronkite moment there should have been uh a time
where people said this this is very stupid what
the heck are we doing let's look at this and never
do it again well i'm in a group with danny shawson
and some veterans that try to do this but again we
can't even get published or if we do get published
it just doesn't even make a difference so i think
it is the fact that they came up with this recipe
for perpetual war and it's really hard to dislodge
this and of course now it's really hard to be a
whistleblower because it's it's it's unlike even
during vietnam where there was a peace movement
what do we have left now we have a handful
of people in church basements singing kumbaya
there's hardly anyone who really is against
war and the media the mainstream media sold out
bought out you know whatever even progressive uh i
hate to say this but even some progressive things
they go for humanitarian war as long as you
can say it's for human rights and democracy
they're all for it too and and again i'm i'm
very cynical about this fact right now that we
we fell for this recipe for perpetual war
and here in the united states it's just very
difficult to be a whistleblower john yeah let me
ask you you uh you know way back 10 years ago uh
you came out there wasn't a massive movement
in support of john kereyaku as well so i mean
is there is there a feeling of loneliness
oh boy isolation and hopelessness i i would
i would defy you to to name one whistleblower
who hasn't considered suicide uh in in his or her
darkest days after going public and
realizing just how little public support
there is out there oh yeah and you know
it's funny too because um after i made my
my revelations i got so many death threats that i
actually had to had to leave the country for for a
couple of weeks my wife and i uh took our kids to
mexico just you know the fbi recommended that we
go on vacation somewhere that at least
two of these threats were credible
and uh we should just make ourselves um scarce and
then i got an email from a retired deputy director
of the cia saying and i'll never forget it i
saved it he said you've chosen a difficult road
but i'm glad somebody did i just wish
i had had the courage to do it myself
that translated into nothing for me no support
at all no public support i was ostracized by
my cia colleagues even if they were whispering
very quietly among themselves that i had done
the right thing but you know randy when the when
the media is controlled by the big corporations
where the big newspapers don't have an
investigative reporting budget anymore so they
rely on on press releases and friendly relations
with the cia's office of public affairs or the
fbi's office of public affairs and they
just gist whatever those offices give them
a whistleblower doesn't have a chance you
don't have a chance because you don't have
the same kind of access to this corporate media
that the rest of them do you're on your own uh
uh dan dan uh so going back to 71 i know you
uh went to um you went to william fulbright and
and you went to um another senator uh back
then uh messiah george mcgovern george robert
mcgovern and matthias also and then and
then uh mike gravel finally read just up
uh on the senate floor but but was it a lonely
experience for you uh at that point in time
uh did you feel the world crashing in on you
that you were like in in a skateboard situation
well there was a big difference there which the
other here to know there was a movement there
was an anti-war movement and it had come out of
a civil rights movement and anti-house american
activities a lot of people have been activists
against that but then a big civil rights movement
and then a big anti-war movement and i'm those
weren't separate because and even the the women's
liberation movement came out of that in part
overlapping in part because the women got sick of
being at the anywhere movement meetings and always
making all the coffee and uh doing the [__] work
of various kinds of not being called on to be real
decision makers and they started having women's
meetings on that literally a lot of it came out
of that out of resentment of the way they've
been treated by us by the white male uh activists
in that part but anyway you had a movement that
people called it the movement they you know
they emphasize one or another part of this
that they come out of but to when we were
finding people to give us place to stay
when uh they're looting the fbi um for 13 days
the person who was organizing that who was an
asian woman who was a harvard janaki general her
name just had to go to almost anybody who had
long hair which in those days was is likely to be
a man as a woman and you go to a young person in
other words and say we have something here that
might help shorten the war and it might be very
dangerous legally are you willing to take part
no one refused they did it so you had a very
different situation there that's nothing like that
exists today how could that be by the way and i
as i was listening to you i thought of one big
difference and that is that in those days 58
000 americans were in the process of being killed
week by week day by day so everybody who family
knew something was involved in that and that
wasn't happening in afghanistan because they
made that award we're all together i think only
at 2400 well i say only because it's the same as
9 11. but over over 20 years that many died as
opposed to 58 000 and the people who were dying
were afghans or iraqis or sudanese you know or
all over the place and the sad thing is uh that
as senator goodell who was run out of
the republican party in 1970 for having
said to end the war he told me just before he
left office dan american people don't care about
vietnamese lives and i said charlie you might be
right i hope you're not right because i think that
nixon's strategy is to remove gradually american
troops out of this and lower the casualties
lower the cost and make it air war where you are
killing vietnamese only not americans well i think
that's what he did intend to do how long could
he have kept that going the answer is afghanistan
20 years could have been longer how many vietnam
how many afghans were killed americans didn't
ask that question i think very few of them have
ever seen an estimate of how many afghans were
killed they don't care uh pilots well they're
volunteers and drones no problem i'm sorry to
say and i don't think it's only americans i think
other members of empires i don't know of a case
where there has been as much resistance as there
was in vietnam or even some of these others
but uh in terms of general acceptance of it that's
the human situation we're dealing in and when you
get a war like afghanistan now is john is involved
with the torture campaign or something like that
he didn't you didn't get the support it wasn't
there yeah well i gotta tell you i was certainly
moved by uh you know i was a draft age in 1973
but it was a standby draft and everyone around me
was against the war and we came out of the civil
rights movement my cousin was an sds speaker so uh
that he had an influence over me and but i look
at the that overall movement you had major support
there julian assange right now does have very
little you know it's it's the whistleblowers it's
people in london is you know it's a scatter shot
here and there where you see people on the street
and you would think that this guy would have major
support uh out there and if he did it would make
his life a lot easier and make the prosecution's
life a lot tougher and i want to talk about the
prosecution in this case uh because we haven't
spoken about that on this show and in particular
gordon uh kromberg and uh the evidence that he
has acquired uh to uh you know come up with these
espionage act charges which are 17. dan you had
13 charges against you under the espionage act
and you uh john had three i believe let's go to
the groundwork where cronberg gets his information
justice department uh colleen and talk about uh
this guy ziggy thordenson i believe his last name
is uh they're using a guy who has like it may
as well be jeffrey dahmer that they got uh to
be the key witness where do they get this why do
they get people like that knowing what a terrible
witness they will be uh they were grasping at
straws that's the short answer they don't have any
witnesses that can actually confirm any charge of
the actual espionage act so they had to get this
kid who's uh uh been already uh connected
to sex abuse of of nine miners uh to
various frauds all kinds of criminality and they
had to go to this lowest level to get him to say
make up a lie that uh assange told me to to
to do some illegal hacking okay so complete
lie now the fbi doesn't care for if they can
make the this is the only way they can uh
support those charges against the espionage act
now they probably are trying to scramble right now
because they don't have a witness their witness
has gone completely south and when that happens
typically the judge as daniel ellsberg will
tell you when you have this kind of criminality
involved in a case typically the judges dismiss
the case you know and and of course there's the
other thing with the spine on assange in the uh
in the embassy as well i mean this this is on
a terrible not only weak and thin case for the
prosecution but now it's gone completely south
so why this continues uh to be why biden does not
go back to what the the prevailing thought was
during the obama administration which is that you
cannot prosecute a a member of the press without
destroying freedom of the press for all of your
mainstream press why he doesn't go back to that
or come up with some excuse to dismiss the charges
at this point because they don't have a case
the the fbi unfortunately and siggy is not
the first really bad criminal that the fbi
has used to either entrap others there's a
case right now in the supreme court where
the informant out in orange county was told to
spy on people in the mosque and the people in
the mosque called the fbi and said there's
a guy trying to provoke us into violence
they they uh they actually tried to uh uh to rat
out their the fbi's own informant he was so bad
he was doing all kinds of terrible things and
that's going to up to the supreme court right now
let's hope that the supreme court can say we the
fbi is not allowed to do this and of course if you
also go back in history fbi operating organized
crime murderers this wasn't a one-year thing they
operate operated those with those top echelon
organized crime murderers like whitey bulger
and scarpa for two decades two decades and the
only reason it went on was because of top secrecy
and only because of a prosecutor a curious
prosecutor and judge did they finally get
into the files to see what was really going
on the fbi does will never reveal those things
they will never reveal because that you know what
they're only rewarded for making cases and uh the
case against assange is a big reward it's just
like what organized crime was back in the 80s
or uh or the uh communism during the 50s under j
edgar hoover there's always a flavor of the day
and when that's the top priority if you can make
a case in that top priority your career is golden
you will go right up to the top just like strzok
and then others in the fbi you'll you'll rise
right up and so there's a lot of incentives
and as long as it's top secret until until
siggy himself outed himself and said no i the
fbi told me to you know got me to lie about this
um how would anyone have ever learned and probably
it would have even gone into court this way
may i ask a question randy i'd like to ask
uh colleen so colleen and i know of course
that you're you're not an attorney in the uk
but if you could give us an educated guess
so here you've got this guy siggy who's
a convicted pedophile and a convicted
embezzler and a liar an admitted liar uh you've
got uh the cia uh hiring this spanish company to
to bug the ecuadorian embassy you've got now the
leaked story that the cia and mi6 conspired to
either kidnap julian or to murder
him in the streets of knightsbridge
judges aren't stupid right that has to play a
role in whatever the the appeals court judges
are discussing right now or beyond that the the
british supreme court or even the european court
of human rights does it not or do they or do they
just keep all of that stuff out of their heads
while they uh debate this case you know it goes
back if if facts mattered if facts mattered in
this orwellian world where we make our own reality
unfortunately the judges right now some judges not
all of them you have to cross your fingers that
you know this judge could at least has a couple of
uh you know conscience and some thinking points
that they can go through the evidence i mean
there's nothing there it's overwhelming yeah uh
that how bad this case is but the judges have are
influenced by other things and loyalty and heaven
knows i mean we've had our officials threatening
uh united nations officials to keep things secret
and to do what they wanted and the united states
does use some really terrible tactics at times
and so who knows who knows what's going to happen
uh but if you just cared about facts if you
just cared about the facts this one this case
would have been dismissed a long time ago because
there's nothing there well let me ask you a dan
uh you had the fbi director was j edgar hoover
you had john mitchell as the u.s attorney
you were facing attorney general i mean attorney
general yes he was the attorney general so uh
what kind of dirty tricks did the fbi play on you
actually it wasn't so much the fbi the uh hoover
apparently in his last year before he died wanted
to leave a better legacy than he was praying up to
be and according to g gordon liddy who had been
in the fbi uh the white house needed its own
criminals because he couldn't count on hoover to
do it without nixon signing off on a petition a
piece of paper actually literally we could go into
this but when hoover when they wanted to get all
the kinds of surveillance that they're
doing now uh the houston plan so-called
and every a lot of crimes provocative things and
so forth and hoover didn't want to do it unless
nixon would sign it personally and to draw back
from it so the white house then did hire its
own ex-fbi and xcia people howard hunt and then a
dozen uh cia assets from the bay of pigs who came
up with orders to on may 3rd 1972 to incapacitate
daniel ellsberg totally and when i heard that
from the special prosecutor with your mural i said
what does that mean tell me and he said the words
were to incapacitate you totally but you have to
understand he said these guys never use the word
kill neutralize terminate with extreme prejudice
various euphemisms he thought their intent was to
kill me but the important thing here is my trial
was ended because those things came out john dean
in particular started you know revealed that one
to the prosecutor and others andy and the burglary
to my former psychoanalyst so you know illegal
wiretaps that i'd been overheard on all the things
that have been used against julian so on the basis
of that one thing after another day after day in
the last wonderful two weeks of my trial after two
years there one crime after another being revealed
that wasn't that was a good time and in the
end he had essentially no choice but to dismiss
the charges people were around the country other
judges were saying why is that trial going on and
the reason was he'd been offered to be head of the
fbi which had been his lifelong ambition since to
replace jade gerhoover who had just died by that
time as head of the fbi so they were heading that
his life's desire in front of him if the ellsberg
case came out all right so the trial kept going
on despite all these trunks but in the end it did
end now the point is here we have exactly the same
stuff discussions of kidnapping not kidnapping
me they had me with discussions of killing him
as was true on may 3rd or incapacity illegal
wiretapping illegal surveillance of his lawyer
meetings in his doctor's meetings of course
it should be thrown out plainly charged
uh and i think if you could count on that
you can't exactly count but the case is there
bush could of course right now simply
drop the appeal to extradite him
just say okay it's over he should drop the
indictment the first indictment of a journalist
ever of course he shouldn't be doing that but
this is the man this he wasn't the dog person
uh back uh under uh under obama he was the
vice president the doj i think was holder
at this point who was a mixed record you know
some good stuff some bad stuff but holder did
not order indict him because it's so blatantly
against the first amendment in my case and all
the others it was a question of sources to the to
the press uh here he julian was in a position like
the new york times in my case well uh that's
that is blatantly against uh freedom of the press
at the same time bush as vice president was saying
this man he was asked is he a high-tech terrorist
yes he's a high-tech terrorist now think about
that a high-tech terrorist for publishing true
information what but this was vice president
and the secretary of state was saying
why don't we drone him and when that came out
said well i was joking but other people there said
it didn't seem to us as though she was joking
and could she have meant that well her boss obama
did drone american citizens without any due
process no indictment no nothing anwar al-salaki
signed off by the president to be assassinated
by a drone program and then for reasons that
have never been explained his 16 year old son
trying to find him before he knew he was dead
is also killed by a drone we've never really
heard what what happened there and of course
they haven't told us another american citizen
by the way so uh when when snowden was uh
in hong kong it turned out but when they
were looking for him they didn't have him yet
i said somewhere he was in danger of his
life and somebody on the atlantic podcast
something like ellensburg is off the wall
here you know he's blown and he's it's crazy
he said you're looking at a
person if you're looking at me
you're looking at a person who had 12 people
brought up from miami in order to the white house
to incapacitate me so i'm not uh i'm not making
this stuff up and that's where we've come to
as a country we'll come back to bush uh
somebody in the uh right i'm sorry to assange
bush is carrying out what he did as vice
president he's still going ahead with it unlike
unlike obama of course he should end this but
here's a very here's a very concrete thing that
might offer some hope i was just told by sulet
dreyfus who was written with assad written books
stuff the other day that i have to look into
this i haven't that there's gonna be a summit
on freedom of the press or freedom of expression
i i maybe you know more about that but she says
something's coming out on that which biden
will attend and this would be a time to say
if you're going to that summit this would be a
good time to say don't extradite julian assange
and if we could get some real pressure frankly his
prospects are not good for getting out of jail for
a very long time even if they don't extradite
him on this our government bush will appeal
outrageously outrageously to do that so if
he's challenged uh with this thing coming up
that may be a time we can do something to say okay
you're talking about freedom of the press and this
case yeah i think we should all be out there
demonstrating when biden goes to this event and
by the way dan uh you know what is the event do
you know it i don't actually haven't heard exactly
i don't i don't know what it is either but
something that he's going to we'll find out here
let's find out i i just want to uh mention
that uh they unleashed the because of you
the plumber squad the plumber squad went
after you and they were they were organized
strictly to go after you and then of course
they went after uh the democratic headquarters
that's what i say is the miracle yeah
right that combination uh seriously
you ended a war and ended a presidency in
one fell through we're gonna take a quick
break and come back uh if you guys would
like to stick around for a little bit more
can i get you to stick around we're gonna say
goodbye to the folks at progressive radio network
and uh after this musical break we'll be right
back with this superstar guest list that we have
so
okay we're back i'm randy credico randy critical
live on the fly with uh john kiriokou colleen
rally and daniel ellsberg john has to leave us
uh here in a minute just john uh quickly uh the
three minutes the guy cromberg the gordon kromberg
what drives this man why isn't he influenced by
all of the things that yeah elaine talked about
you know i i i hate to sound cynical but the truth
is that that so many of these u.s attorneys
or resistant u.s attorneys especially the
senior ones like cronberg you know they see great
futures for themselves as partners in a-list firms
as congressional candidates maybe as candidates
for governor someday there's always something
bigger something better on the horizon
and if they can pull a rudy giuliani
uh and and prosecute a big name uh in a big case
then the next thing they do is they announce
their candidacy for for congress or they uh make a
call to um you know aiken gump and strauss and say
hey i'm available right now at 10 times what
i make with the justice department so it's a
selfish motivation it's all about self-promotion
shameless self-promotion sean when you say
you hate to sound cynical i agree at night
with lily tomlins and who said in her show
no matter how cynical you try
to be you can't keep up with it
i know you gotta go now we're gonna say goodbye
to you and spend a few more minutes have a great
night everybody thank you and thank you randy
for the work that you do great to see everybody
all right we'll see you john john kiriakou bye-bye
my heroes uh whistleblower his book is coming out
it's uh several whistleblowers 15 whistleblowers
and uh we are talking with colleen rowley
and with daniel ellsberg colleen uh let's uh
these concluding moments uh an overall assessment
uh what you've been watching in the assange
case uh what is it at the heart of it that is
driving you crazy uh the situation is driving
i think not only me i i heard katie halper and
it's like being in the twilight zone um again i
i go back to karl rove's famous thing you know
we can make our own reality and after 9 11 when
when the uh when they saw how fear worked so well
to be able to manipulate the public and how the
donations to the media you know from all of these
corporate sources and the war machine and uh you
know that basically all they have to do is very
easy job read the government press releases and
you know the talking points that are given to them
uh this makes for a world that you can hardly
believe you're living in this situation right
now so you know the assange cases is is a victim
of this really i mean orwellian gets said a lot um
but it's an it's an empire of lies where lemmings
are just being led over the cliff and yet when the
like that you know the emperor's new clothes the
little boy yells out you know he's naked he's
naked the crowd turns on the little boy and says
uh no we support the empire we support the emperor
i mean and and if you're watching this and of
course having had some even personal experience in
this in the beginning of the post 9 11 stuff it's
really disconcerting i agree with uh with tomlin
because you know i i find myself becoming so
cynical that i i wonder if i can get more cynical
at this point hardly believe anything uh off the
the mainstream news and you are hard-pressed to
search online for uh at this point a handful i'll
put you randy in that group you know a handful
of voices now that i can actually feel like
okay that person has a little bit of integrity
uh unlike you know the cronkite moment
where we had sixty percent of the of the
american population that did trust and you know
cronkite might have had his bad moments too but
there was that trust and i don't think now i
i'm on greenwald writes about this all the time
how can you trust anybody in the media who has
these incentives these very perverse incentives
so um wikileaks was an exception to that we
somehow someway have to get back to that kind of
ability to get some truth out and maybe it
would be a good first step if we could put
pressure on biden to have this extradition
request uh dropped and maybe that would it
would obviously just be the very first step but
maybe that would be a step in the right direction
of getting back to a little bit of truth right now
all right uh dan uh i'm gonna ask you this uh if
if you uh if you had a chance to talk to julian
assange at this moment what would you say to him
well i told his wife and i told celeb
who's dreyfuss is in touch with him uh
tell him i love him that was supporting
him and that he has a lot of supporters
out here as we've been saying he doesn't
have the movement that existed in my day
i was called a traitor by the
president and by the vice president
but uh there were a lot of people who didn't agree
with that and i had i had a lot of support as well
and uh and there are people i'm i'm struck by
how many people do turn out in the rain and cold
in london both when he was in ecuador at embassy
and now it is striking how many people do come out
more i think possibly over there than over here
i'm not sure i have been in demonstrations over
here for but uh not as much but i just wanted
to know that there are people out here who who
do support what what he stands for and he was
telling the truth about uh about the war with
publishing what chelsea manning was was giving
him at that time and so both of them i think
deserve great uh thanks for the american people
for what i want to ask you both one last question
and i'm going to go with you first colleen uh
what's the consequences ultimate consequences
if assange is brought to this country
is convicted and sent to prison
i i think one of the consequences which
is end of all press freedom i mean it's
it's really hanging by a string right now and
you know i think you could argue that it's
you know with the scissors you know ready to be
cut that little thin string freedom of the press
is the censorship you know government leaning on
social media everything that's going on right now
i think that for sure if this goes any
further we will not have a first amendment
uh in any meaningful sense we
will not have a first amendment
and if as snowden has said many many times tom
drake snowden and many other whistleblowers
once you lose the freedom of press that first
amendment is i think thomas jefferson he made it
first it's it's the number one thing and once you
don't have any ability to dissent in a democracy
no ability to get the truth out well the
whole country will be like the informant files
okay a locked skiff room that you have to have a
key to go into there will be absolutely no ability
to have democracy if we lose that first amendment
and it's hanging by a thread right now and uh you
dan uh in the closing you get to you get the
andy rooney a moment here what would you say uh
the consequences of an assange conviction
oh that's that's very clear because
he is the first time that a president has dared to
use the espionage act or any other right against a
journalist at this point as he is indicted and if
he were extradited in the current climate i think
his chance of being acquitted which was possible
in my day with the judge who did recognize that
it was unconstitutional what was happening there
he put off a judgment on that until the end of the
trial and then the government's criminality forced
all that so it didn't get judged didn't get ruled
on if he is convicted and that is uphill then
the first amendment will essentially be nullified
as far as national security so-called and
of course what is this national security
i've never asked this before let me put it this
way which american who's died for his in uniform
has done so actually for the national
security of this country since 1945
in which of our wars was our national security
actually involved and where they actually hate
to say this to the families of people who
have lost man mostly men some women now but
to say their lives were wasted in an unjust
cause they were fighting courageously in most
cases in an unjust cause and the only way we know
that largely is from the accuracy the honesty
that has come through along with a lot of lies
and a lot of emotions from the press so i go
back to nathan hale the american revolution gave
us a free first amendment eventually not at first
uh free to impress england doesn't have
that still they have an official secrets act
and if we lose that first amendment and we will
have in effect than an official secret sect
and all you will have are government handouts
and that will give us more vietnam more iraq's
obviously the freedom of the press did
not perform as it should have to keep us
out of vietnam or out of iraq earlier it failed
on that but uh we would have been in a lot longer
uh and more without such freedom as there was so
if we lose that uh the empire will be due even
more evil than it is doing now and has done in the
past well well said i want to thank both of you
uh and john kiriakou uh colleen rally and daniel
ellsberg three times in three weeks we've had the
pleasure of having you on this show zero times in
the first five years but really it was worth the
wait because you have just been fabulous thank
you for uh being so uh generous with your time
and thank both of you for the uh sacrifices you
have made in your lifetime and and uh for your
support of julian assange god knows he needs it
and he needs all he can get i'm randy credico
this has been randy critical live on the fly with
a special edition of assange countdown to freedom
uh we'll see you uh next week thank you very
much both of you everybody dice are knows
everybody rolls with their fingers crossed
everybody knows the war is over everybody knows
everybody knows that the fight was fixed the poor
stay poor the rich get rich that's how it goes
everybody know everybody knows that
the boat is leaking everybody knows
everybody got this broken feeling like their
father or their dog just died everybody
talking to their pockets everybody wants a box of
chocolates and a long stem room everybody knows